<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Babylon's fall in Maryland, a fair warning to Lord Baltamore, or, A relation of an assault made by divers papists, and popish officers of the Lord Baltamore's, against the Protestants in Maryland to whom God gave a great victory against a greater force of souldiers and armed men, who came to destroy them / published by Leonard Strong, agent for the people of Providence in Maryland.</title>
            <author>Strong, Leonard, Agent for the people of Providence in Maryland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61841</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5994</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17655</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13038548</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13038548</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96856</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61841)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96856)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 400:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Babylon's fall in Maryland, a fair warning to Lord Baltamore, or, A relation of an assault made by divers papists, and popish officers of the Lord Baltamore's, against the Protestants in Maryland to whom God gave a great victory against a greater force of souldiers and armed men, who came to destroy them / published by Leonard Strong, agent for the people of Providence in Maryland.</title>
                  <author>Strong, Leonard, Agent for the people of Providence in Maryland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 11, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestants --  Maryland.</term>
               <term>Maryland --  History --  Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96856:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96856:1"/>
            <p>BABYLON's Fall in <hi>MARYLAND:</hi> A fair WARNING to Lord <hi>Baltamore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR, A RELATION Of an Aſſault made by divers Papiſts, and Popiſh Officers of the Lord
<hi>Balta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi>'s againſt the Proteſtants in <hi>Maryland;</hi> to whom GOD gave a great
Victory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a greater force of Souldiers and armed Men, who came to deſtroy them.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by <hi>Leonard Strong,</hi> Agent for the people of PROVIDENCE in MARY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND.</p>
            <p>Printed for the Author, 1655.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:96856:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96856:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Babylons</hi> fall in <hi>Maryland.</hi> A fair warning to Lord
<hi>Baltamore.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the yeer 1649. many, both of the congregated Church, and other well-affected people in
<hi>Virginia,</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred from the free exerciſe of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, under the Government of
Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Barkely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> removed themſelves, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and Eſtates into the
Province of <hi>Maryland,</hi> being thereunto invited by Captain <hi>William Stone,</hi> then
Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for Lord <hi>Baltamore,</hi> with promiſe of Liberty in Religion, and Priviledges of
Engliſh Subjects.</p>
            <p>An Oath to the Lord <hi>Baltamore</hi> was urged upon this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſoon after their coming up,
which if they did not take, they muſt have no Land, nor abiding in the Province. This Oath was
very ſcrupulouſly looked upon: firſt, In regard it bindes to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and be ſubject to
a Royal Juriſdiction and abſolute Dominion of the Lord <hi>Baltamore,</hi> and to defend it and
him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all power whatſoever. This was thought far too high for him, being a Subject, to
exact upon ſuch terms as it was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, and too much unſutable to the preſent liberty which
God had given the Engliſh Subjects, from Arbitrary and Popiſh Government; as the Lord
<hi>Baltamore</hi>'s Government doth plainly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96856:3"/>appear to be. Secondly, It was exceedingly ſcrupled on another account,
<hi>viz.</hi> That they muſt ſwear to uphold that Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and thoſe Officers who are
ſworn to countenance and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Antichriſt, in plain words expreſt in the Officers Oath, the
Roman Catholick Religion. And for theſe people to own ſuch by an Oath, whom in their hearts
they could by no means cloſe with; what could it be accounted, but <hi>Colluſion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet nevertheleſs the people that were then come up to <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> conſidering Lord
<hi>Baltamore</hi> to be Lord of the ſoil, and willing to acknowledge him, and pay him his due
Rents and Services; upon that account took an Oath which was much qualified and moderated from its
former rigour: but this, though it was accepted by Captain <hi>Stone</hi> the Lord
<hi>Baltamore</hi>'s Lieutenant, yet utterly rejected by his Lordſhip, who gave or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, That the
Oath abſolutely ſhould be urged; and gave ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial inſtructions and charge to his
Leiutenant to proclaim, That all that would not take the Oath within three Months after
publication, and pay Rents, and ſue out Patents, ſhould be expulſed the Province, and the
Land ſeized to his Lordſhips uſe; who required his Officers to ſee the contents of the
Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation executed.</p>
            <p>Now the people having been formerly ſenſible of ſuch yokes, impoſed contrary to what was
promiſed them before they came into the Province, complained by their Agent in
<hi>England,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, to the Lord <hi>Baltamore,</hi> deſiring his Lordſhip, That ſuch burthens as the
Oath and other great inconveniences men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in our inſtructions, might be removed. But the
Lord <hi>Baltamore</hi> rejected the motion. Our Agent preſented a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the then Councel
of State, where it hath been depending neer four yeers, without any hearing, Anſwer or Relief;
which hath brought unſpeakable troubles upon this Province, &amp; now at laſt occaſioned the
ſhedding of much Engliſh blood; yea, of the Saints in <hi>Maryland.</hi> God grant that Right
and Juſtice may have a more open courſe to flow into all the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of <hi>England,</hi>
without obſtructions; and, that innocent blood be not ſhed any more for want thereof.</p>
            <p>In the yeer 1652. <hi>Richard Bennet</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Colonel <hi>William Clayborne,</hi>
and Captain <hi>Edmund Curtis,</hi> Commiſſioners from
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96856:3"/>the Supream Authority of the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> arrived in
<hi>Maryland,</hi> in the <hi>Guiny</hi> Friggot to reduce that Province into the obedience of the
Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> according to their Commiſſion; which was effected by them,
firſt, in their taking away the Commiſſions and Powers of the Lord <hi>Baltamore,</hi> in the
hands of Captain <hi>William Stone</hi> his Governour, and <hi>Thomas Hatton</hi> his Secretary,
and the reſt of the Lord <hi>Baltamores</hi> Councel; as they had very good cauſe ſo to do;
for none of the Engliſh Dominions had more need of being reduced; and cauſed them to take the
Engagement to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of <hi>England,</hi> as it was then, without King or Houſe of
Lords. And ſo they might have continued in their places ſtill, onely to the Commonwealth of
<hi>England;</hi> but they would not yield to iſſue out Writs in any other name, then Lord
<hi>Balta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi>'s, becauſe of their Oath to him.</p>
            <p>In the yeer 1654. upon ſome Inſtructions and Relations from the Lord <hi>Baltamore</hi> out
of <hi>England,</hi> Captain <hi>William Stone,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Thomas Hatton,</hi> and the
Popiſh Councellors, roſe up againſt the Reducement, diſplacing thoſe whom the States
Commiſſioners had placed, and introducing the old Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Councel; calling that which was
done by commiſſion from the Councel of State in <hi>England,</hi> Rebellion againſt the Lord
<hi>Baltamore;</hi> and thoſe that were Actors in it, Factious and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Perſons: which
was done by a Proclamation full of railing terms, publiſhed at <hi>Providence</hi> in the
Church-meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Commiſſioners for the Commonwealth of England, hearing that new Orders and
Inſtructions were come to Maryland from Lord</hi> Baltamore, <hi>and that one</hi> Scarborough
<hi>a miſchievous inſtrument of the Lord</hi> Baltamore <hi>was gone up</hi> Maryland,
<hi>reſolved to come and ſee in what condition their affairs ſtood.</hi> And finding a direct
contradiction to, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding from that obedience to the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> which
was promiſed, but not performed, by the Lord <hi>Baltamore</hi>'s Officers, applied themſelves
in a peaceable and loving way to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them into their due and promiſed obedience, yet
became the ſaid Commiſſioners were given to underſtand, That there was a miſchievous
deſign by Lord <hi>Baltamore</hi>'s Officers and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96856:4"/>their Complices, to apprehend their perſons, and to raiſe Forces againſt
the lawful Power of the Commonwealth of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſaid Commiſſioners deſired ſome to come down from <hi>Providence,</hi> and ſome
from <hi>Putuxent</hi> to guard their Perſons, and defend themſelves &amp; people from that
power of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Arms, which by this time Captain <hi>Stone</hi> had preſſed in Lord
<hi>Balta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi>'s name, upon pain of death to aſſiſt him againſt the ſaid
Commiſſioners, and gathered together in a formidable manner. But the ſaid Commiſſioners
being greatly deſirous of peace, and willing to avoid the ſhedding of blood, applyed
themſelves to the ſaid Captain <hi>Stone<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> to bring him to a parley and conference;
where, after ſome arguing, the ſaid Captain <hi>Stone</hi> reſigned up the Government which
he took up in the Lord <hi>Baltamore</hi>'s name, into the hand of the Commiſſioners of
<hi>England;</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing to be obedient to that Government, which by their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
ſhould be ſet over them, under his Highneſs the Lord Protector.</p>
            <p>The ordering and governing the affairs of <hi>Maryland,</hi> was then committed to Captain
<hi>Will. Fuller,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rich. Preſton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Richard Durand,</hi> Mr. <hi>Edward
Lloyd,</hi> &amp;c. others mentioned in the Commiſſion, who were required to attend the
Engagement of the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> to keep Courts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to
ſummon an Aſſembly in <hi>October</hi> following. At this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly there was a full and
lawful Repreſentative of the whole Province, where the Act of Reducement of this Province by
Commiſſion from the Councel of State in <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Richard Bennet</hi>
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Colonel <hi>William Cleyborne, Emund Curtis,</hi> was freely and fully
acknowledged by the whole Aſſembly; the Burgeſſe of every reſpective County and Limit
confirming the ſame, and ſubmitting thereunto. And did paſs, and record an Act, <hi>That
whoſoever did publiſh any Writ or Summons, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration or Proclamation, either in the
Lord</hi> Baltamore<hi>'s or any other name, then the Government ſo ſetled as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid had
and received, ſhould be accounted a Delinquent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Commonwealth of England, and dealt
with accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame Aſſembly did make Proteſtation againſt a Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96856:4"/>ſent over by his Lordſhip, and recorded by his Secretary; wherein the ſaid
Lord did declare the people at <hi>Providence,</hi> by him called <hi>Annardundel,</hi> to be
Rebels; and ſtrictly charged his Officers efficaciouſly to deal with them accordingly: but no
ground or reaſon thereof could be found, But their not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with his Arbitrary and
Popiſh Government, and the adhering to the Engagement and the Reducement aforeſaid, and
Government ſetled by the aforeſaid Commiſſioners.</p>
            <p>After this Aſſembly, the Province was quiet, and ſo continued until the later end of
<hi>January;</hi> about which time, the Ship <hi>Golden Fortune,</hi> whereof Captain
<hi>Tilman</hi> was Commander, arrived in <hi>Maryland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then the Lord <hi>Baltamore</hi>'s Officers, and the Popiſh party began to divulge abroad, and
boaſt much of power which came in that Ship from his Highneſs the Lord Protector, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm
the Lord <hi>Baltamore</hi>'s Patent to him, and to re-eſtabliſh his Officers in their former
places under him: which pretended power they aſſumed to themſelves; Captain <hi>Stone</hi>
and the reſt giving out threatning ſpeeches, That now the Rebels at <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuxent</hi> and
<hi>Severne,</hi> ſhould know that he was Governour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; giving Order, That neither Act of the
ſaid Aſſembly ſhould be obſerved, nor Writ from the power eſtabliſhed by the
Commiſſioners aforeſaid obeyed, but what ſhould iſſue forth in the name of the Lord
Proprietory, <hi>viz.</hi> Lord <hi>Baltamore.</hi> And further, the ſaid Captain <hi>Stone</hi>
gave ſeveral Commiſſions to the Papiſts and other deſperate and bloody fellows, to
muſter and raiſe men in arms to be ready upon all occaſions, giving out that he would go to
<hi>Putuxent,</hi> and ſeize the Records of the Province at the place where they were appointed
to be kept by an Act of the Aſſembly, and to apprehend Mr. <hi>Richard Preſton</hi> alſo,
at whoſe houſe they were; which ſhortly after was effected by Vertue of a Warrant in Captain
<hi>Stone</hi>'s name, without Proclaiming, or ſhewing any power by which he acted ſuch high
Robberies. But in threatning ſpeeches declared, That they would have the Government; and for the
terror of others, would hang ſome of the Commiſſioners, which were entruſted with the
Government by the Commiſſioners of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>England,</hi> under his Highneſs
the Lord Protector,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96856:5"/>namely, Captain <hi>William Fuller,</hi> Mr. <hi>Richard Preſton,</hi> and Mr.
<hi>William Durand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About this time Captain <hi>William Fuller,</hi> Mr. <hi>William Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand,</hi> Mr. <hi>Leonard
Strong,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Richard Ewen,</hi> to whom among others the Government was committed,
ſent two Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of quality and truſt with Letters to Captain <hi>Stone,</hi> in a way
of peace and love; deſiring him to make it known by what power he ſurpriſed the Records; and
deſiring him, the ſaid Captain <hi>Stone<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> to give an Anſwer, as by the Letter,
relation thereunto being had, more at large appeareth: But the ſaid Captain <hi>Stone,</hi>
inſtead of giving a ſatisfactory Anſwer, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned the Meſſengers, and in much wrath
and ſury ſaid he would ſhew no power: at laſt he affirmed, that he acted by a power from
Lord <hi>Baltamore;</hi> and that the Lord Protector had confirmed the Lord <hi>Baltamore</hi>'s
power. If ſo, Sir, ſaid one of the Meſſengers, if it be confirmed, let that appear, and it
will ſatisfie. Confirmed, ſaid Captain <hi>Stone,</hi> I'll confirm it; and ſo ſent them
home. After this, the ſaid Captain <hi>Stone</hi> and his Officers proceeded in their wicked
deſign; yet to colour it over, the ſaid Captain <hi>Stone</hi> publiſhed a Proclamation to
deceive the amazed and diſtracted people at <hi>Putuxent;</hi> wherein he called God to
witneſs, that he intended not to uſe any hoſtile way to them or the people at
<hi>Providence.</hi> Which Proteſtation how falſe and feigned it was, the following proceedings
of himſelf and Officers, will clearly evidence to all the World: for notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this
Proclamation and Proteſtation, the ſaid Captain <hi>Stone</hi> ſent up to <hi>Putuxent</hi>
one <hi>William Eltonhead</hi> and <hi>Joſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Fendal,</hi> and with them twenty men in Arms, who
did beſet and entred the houſe of Mr. <hi>Richard Preſton,</hi> with intent to ſurpriſe
him; but not finding him at home, took away in Guns, Swords and Ammunition to the value of 30
<hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> ſterling;</hi> ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cked
every place in and about the houſe, to ſeek for the ſaid <hi>Richard Preſton;</hi> and as
ſome of the Company then ſaid, with purpoſe to hang him for his rebellion againſt the Lord
<hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamore.</hi> At the ſame time they ſurpriſed <hi>John Sutton,</hi> who was appointed
by the Aſſembly and Secretary to attend the Records, for any that ſhould have occaſion to
uſe them, either for ſearch or Copy; and carried him away Priſoner with ſuch
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96856:5"/>Guns and Ammunition he had, and kept him about twenty dayes; even ſo they dealt
with Lieutenant <hi>Peter Johnſon;</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other houſes at <hi>Putuxent,</hi> they
ſerved in the like kinde. And when they were deſired to ſhew by what power or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
they ſo acted, they would in a proud bravado clap their hands on their ſwords, and ſay, Here
is a Commiſſion. This was no ſooner effected at <hi>Putuxent,</hi> but preſently they
muſtered in Arms two hundred or two hundred and fifty men at the houſe of the aforeſaid
<hi>Eltonhead,</hi> which <hi>Eltonhead</hi> and <hi>Fendal</hi> ſent up by night ſeveral Boats
with armed men, and forced many of <hi>Putuxen</hi> whether they would or not to go with them upon
their warlike Expedition to <hi>Providence;</hi> taking all the Guns, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Shot, and
Proviſion, they could anywhere finde. And when they had done what they pleaſed at
<hi>Putuxent,</hi> they bent all their Forces towards <hi>Providence,</hi> the chief place of the
reſidence of moſt of the Commiſſioners, and people that were forced out of
<hi>Virginia</hi> by Sir <hi>William Barkely</hi> for conſcience ſake. Some of the ſaid
Company marching by Land, others by Water; they that marched by Land, did much ſpoil and robbery
in all the Houſes and Plantations where they came, breaking open Doors, Trunks and Cheſts. In
this barbarous manner they carried it for about forty miles.</p>
            <p>Now again the Commiſſioners at <hi>Providence</hi> ſent other Meſſengers with a Letter
to Captaine <hi>Stone,</hi> ſtill complaining his proceedings, and ſeeking the knowledge of his
power; and that ſome better accommodation might be attended to prevent the ruine and deſolation
of the whole Province, which this courſe was very likely to bring to paſs. If he were
reſolved to come to no Parley or Treaty, they proteſted in the ſaid writing, that by the help
of God, they were reſolved to commit themſelves into the hand of God, and rather die like men,
then live like ſlaves. This was alſo rejected by the ſaid Captain <hi>Stone</hi> and his
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices, the Meſſengers apprehended, their Boat ſeized, and onely three of ſix eſcaped
to bring the report of their deſperate and bloody deſign, and that they were upon their march
in a hoſtile way.</p>
            <p>Capt. <hi>Stone</hi> and his Company ſtill drew neerer to <hi>Providence,</hi> unto a place
called <hi>Herring-Creek,</hi> where they apprehended
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96856:6"/>one of the Commiſſioners, and forced another man of quality to flie for his
life, having threatned to hang him up-at-his own door; and not finding the man, affrighted his
wife, and plundered the houſe of Ammunition and Proviſion, threatning ſtill what they would
do to the people at <hi>Providence,</hi> and that they would force the rebellious factious
Roundheads to ſubmit; and then they would ſhew their power.</p>
            <p>Having now left the Country behinde them bare of men, ſave onely ſuch as fled into the Woods
from their cruelty and rapine, as alſo of Arms and Ammunition; the poor women urging this to
them, What ſhould they do if the Indians ſhould come upon them, being thus ſtrip'd of men and
Arms to defend them; and in what a ſad and ſorrowful condition they were left: Theſe
mercileſs men anſwered ſcoffingly, It matters not, your ſorrow is our joy.</p>
            <p>And indeed, it is too apparent, that the Indians waited upon their motions, and by examination
it was found at <hi>Providence,</hi> that the Indians were reſolved in themſelves, or ſet on
by the Popiſh faction, or rather both together to fall upon us: as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed after the fight they
did, beſetting houſes, killing one man, and taking another priſoner.</p>
            <p>Now the people at <hi>Providence</hi> perceiving ſuch a tempeſt ready to fall upon them, and
all meſſages rejected, prepared for their coming, looking up, and crying to the Lord of Hoſts
and King of <hi>Ston,</hi> for counſel, ſtrength and courage, being reſolved in the
ſtrength of God to ſtand on their Guard, and demand an account of theſe proceedings, ſeeing
no other remedy, for ſo great a miſchief, could be found.</p>
            <p>About this time Captain <hi>Stone</hi> ſent two men to publiſh a Proclamation quite
againſt the Law eſtabliſhed by the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners of the Commonwealth of
<hi>England,</hi> and againſt an Act of a lawful Aſſembly; which being read, and having no
other Treaty to offer, they were quietly diſmiſſed to their own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, to whom they might
have gone if they would.</p>
            <p>That night Captain <hi>Stone</hi> and his Army appeared in the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of <hi>Severne</hi> at
<hi>Providence,</hi> with eleven or twelve Veſſels greater and leſſer, ſome of which had
plundred by the way, in which their whole Army were wafted.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96856:6"/>
            <p>Capt. <hi>Fuller</hi> &amp; the Councel of War appointed at <hi>Providence</hi> Mr. <hi>Wil.
Durand,</hi> Secretary, to go aboard the <hi>Golden Lion</hi> which then lay at Anchor in the
River, and to fix a Proclamation in the main maſt, directed to Captain <hi>Heamans,</hi>
Commander of the ſaid Ship, wherein he was required in the name of the Lord Protector, and
Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> and for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the juſt Libertyes, Lives, and
Eſtates of the free Subjects thereof, againſt an unjuſt power, to be aiding and
aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in this ſervice.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Captain <hi>Heamans</hi> at firſt was unwilling; but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſeeing the
equity of the Cauſe, and the groundleſs proceedings of the Enemy, he offered himſelf, Ship,
and Men for that ſervice, to be directed by the ſaid <hi>William Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Enemy was come within the command of the Ship at the ſhutting in of the evening: the
Captain of the Ship was required to command them aboard by a piece of Ordnance. The Enemy with a
great noiſe rejected the warning. Then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Piece was levelled where they heard the Boats
rowing; the ſhot whereof lighting ſomething neer, but doing no hurt; A Meſſenger came
aboard; but had nothing of any meſſage to deliver, ſave onely, that Captain <hi>Stone</hi>
thought the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Ship had been ſatisfied. To which the Captain anſwered, Satisfied,
with what? I never ſaw any power Captain <hi>Stone</hi> had, to do as he hath done; but the
ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſcription of a Letter. I muſt, and will, appear for theſe in a good Cauſe.</p>
            <p>That night the Enemy run into the Creek, where they landed out of the reach of the Ship.</p>
            <p>But in the morning, all their Veſſels were block'd up by a ſmall Barque with two pieces of
Ordinance, which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to lie in the mouth of the Creek, and ſo kept from coming
out.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96856:7"/>
            <p>The ſame day being the firſt day of the week, and the 25 of <hi>March,</hi> the Enemy
appeared in a body upon a narrow neck of the Land, neer their Veſſels, and with Drums and
ſhoutings ſaid, <hi>Come ye Rogues, come ye Rogues, Roundheaded Dogs;</hi> which cauſed the
Captain of the Ship to give fire at them, and forced them to march further off, into the neck of
Land.</p>
            <p>In the mean time Capt. <hi>Will. Fuller</hi> with his Company came up the River with ſhoutings
and couragious rejoycings, and landed with a hundred and twenty men, ſix mile diſtant from the
Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: and immediately ſent away all their Sioaps and Boats, committing themſelves into the
hand of God: he marched di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly where the Enemy lay waiting for him. The Enemies Sentry ſhot;
immediately they appeared in order. Captain <hi>Fuller</hi> ſtill expecting, that then at laſt,
poſſibly they might give a reaſon of their coming, commanded his men upon pain of death not
to ſhoot a Gun, or give the firſt onſet; ſetting up the Standard of the Commonwealth of
<hi>England:</hi> againſt which, the Enemy ſhot five or ſix Guns, and killed one man in the
front before a ſhot was made by the other. Then the word was given, <hi>In the Name of God fall
on; God is our Strength,</hi> that was the Word for <hi>Providence:</hi> the <hi>Marylanders</hi>
Word was <hi>Hey for Saint Maries.</hi> The Charge was fierce and ſharp for the time; but through
the glorious preſence of the Lord of Hoſts manifeſted in and towards his poor oppreſſed
people, the Enemy could not endure, but gave back; and were ſo effectually charged home, that
they were all routed, turned their backs, threw down their Arms, and begged mercy. After the
firſt Volley of ſhot, a ſmall Company of the Enemy, from behinde a great tree fallen, galled
us, and wounded divers of our men, but were ſoon beaten off. Of the whole company of the
<hi>Marylanders</hi> there eſcaped onely four or five, who run away out of the Army to carry News
to their Confederates, Captain <hi>Stone,</hi> Colonel <hi>Price,</hi> Captain <hi>Gerrard.</hi>
Captain <hi>Lewis,</hi> Captain <hi>Hendall,</hi> Captain <hi>Guither,</hi> Major
<hi>Chandler,</hi> and all the reſt of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors Officers and Souldiers of the Lord
<hi>Baltamore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> among whom, both Commanders and Souldiers, a great number being
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96856:7"/>Papiſts, were taken, and ſo were all their Veſſels, Arms, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition,
proviſion; about fifty men ſlain and wounded. We loſt onely two in the field; but two died
ſince of their wounds. God did appear wonderful in the field, and in the hearts of the people;
all confeſſing him to be the onely Worker of this victory and deliverance.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Examinatur per me,</hi> William Durand, Secretary of
MARYLAND.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:96856:8"/>
            <head>The Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>THus God our Strength appeared for us; and the blood which they thirſted after in others, was
given to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to drink; the miſeries which they threatned to the innocent, fell upon the
guilty; the pit which they digged for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, themſelves fell into; the cords which they brought
to binde us, bound themſelves. This is the Lord's doing, it may well be marvellous in our
eyes.</p>
            <p>What hath been written, is but a very abstract of thoſe great and various providences of God
toward his people, and against Antichrist; a great Volume would not contain the wonders which the
Lord himſelf hath wrought and manifested to the hearts of his people in this diſpenſation.
The ſum is, Satan and his ſeed, riſing up againſt the ſeed of the woman, bruiſes the
heel of Chriſt, but deſtroyes himſelf utterly. The further evil men proceed in their own way,
the neerer to deſtruction: ſo is it with all fleſh, it works it ſelf into ruine, through
the adored depths of the wiſdom of God.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who are acquainted with the clear and familiar ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances of God to his people in
times of distreſs, can underſtand and rejoyce in what may be now a little further hinted.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Lord confounded the Language of <hi>Babel</hi> in the hearts, projects, and
conſultations of his people, when they were deviſing to defend themſelves from this danger,
till they came to that condition of <hi>Jehoſaphat, We know not what to do, but our eyes are
towards thee; wilt thou judge them? for we have no ſtrength againſt this multitude.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:96856:8"/>
            <p>Secondly, Now the Lord gives teſtimony from himſelf in the Spirits of many of his Saints, in
a wonderful, plain, yet glorious manner; (for the ſecret of the Lord is with them that fear him)
ſo that as well women as men ſpake, or rather God ſpake in them an expreſs teſtimony what
ſhould be the iſſue of this conflict, that is, glory to God in the higheſt, deliverance to
his people, deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to <hi>Babylon,</hi> Songs unto <hi>Sion:</hi> which was revealed ſo
power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, evidently, and certainly, that it raviſh'd the hearts of ſome, aſtoniſh'd
others, and encouraged the heart both of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, Captains, and Souldiers, as well as others that
could not fight, to a Triumph before the Engagement, and the enjoyment of a victory by the
aſſurance of faith, before one ſtroke of the battle.</p>
            <p>The bow of the Lord was made quite bare, to be ſeen of all that had an eye to ſee, &amp; his
arrows were ſeen to be ſharp in the heart of the Kings enemies before they fell under him. God
made the feeble to be as <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>David</hi> as God: they were carried out in the
ſtrength of the Lord, who gave this teſtimony to one of the Captains, juſt as the Enemy came
up, <hi>The Victory is yours; but God ſhall be ſeen, and not man in it.</hi> After the battle,
what acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of God in is was in every mean Souldiers mouth, as well as the Commanders,
what praiſing of God, is beyond expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. They run through all the Company, <hi>Give God
the glory, Bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
